I would say my youngest patients tend to
be, you know, in their in their mid to
mid20s, early 30s. Um, you know, a lot
of my slightly younger patients, again,
it's just a lot of education. Um, you
know, I I for one, again, do do not
believe that a young man should not be
able to have access to something like
testosterone if they need it. Um, you
know, but you and I both know also there
are young men who are not eating the way
they should, are not sleeping the way
they should, training the way they
should. So, you know, I I do start
conservatively. Um, if there's a way in
which we can, you know, not necessarily
prevent you from using testosterone, but
push you in a position where you
potentially don't need it. I I'd rather
go in that direction first. Um, but
again, a lot of my young men uh are born
um I like to say behind the eightball in
the sense that they they they had no
real shot at ever having normal hormone
levels. So then it becomes a lot of
education around well how can we
maintain testicular function? Um would
would the addition of hCG uh be
appropriate in this situation? If you
can't afford hCG, you know, could we
consider testosterone and then
potentially adding hCG in the future? We
talk about crier preservation, you know,
as as kind of a golden insurance policy
around that sort of thing. Um, and I'll
tell you, my young men have just been so
um appreciative because again, they have
been kicked around by probably beginning
with their pediatrician to then their
primary care provider for so long. Um, I
think it just feels validating and and
rewarding to actually, you know, be able
to speak about these things and not be
embarrassed uh to ask for testosterone
like as if they're some sort of, you
know, drug abusing bodybuilder or
something crazy like that. And, uh, why
do they come to your practice? Because
they're already experiencing some low
testosterone symptoms. Yeah, the vast
majority of them uh, do uh, you know,
and and I think most of them, I'm very
fortunate, most of them are referrals
from other young men who have been in
similar positions. Um, similarly, I I
see a lot of females uh and and they,
you know, maybe they're in their mid 20s
or early 30s and they're saying, "Gosh,
Nico, I'm feeling so much better. My
cycles are so much more regular. My
libido is fantastic. You know, my
boyfriend, he's been on a Zoloft for,
you know, 10 years and he's miserable. I
I I'd be curious if you could help him."
So, it's a really nice, again, I love
seeing both sexes for that reason
because we we get a lot of referrals
that way, which is great. All right. So
um why why why do women come to your
practice? Are they also experiencing
some test um hormone related symptoms?
Absolutely. Um you know I I I think
females probably just certainly beat us
in terms of feeling worse than we do and
and I think a big position or a big part
of that is probably because of that
estrogen disrupting uh endocrine
disrupting chemicals the the estrogen
mimicking hormones. Um, women, young
women especially, produce tremendous
amount of estrogen. Most of them do. Uh,
that's that's the game is they produce a
ton of estrogen. Uh, and they turn into
these beautiful young women and then
they start producing a ton of
progesterone and it should flip back and
forth essentially throughout the cycle.
Um, and and I kind of think of it almost
as probably they're experiencing a
stacking effect where now they're around
constantly these xenoestrogens, these
fake estrogens, and that's on top of
their already quite high estrogen loads
that they're producing. And that's
slowly also pushing down their
progesterone. Um, and and all the
typical female problems that exist are
all, generally speaking, low
progesterone problems and high estrogen
problems. So we think you know from the
most severe uh PCOS or polycystic
ovarian syndrome uh endometriosis
uh you know certain types of uh um
mental health issues especially like
premenstrual dysphoric disorder um these
are if you're looking at the data these
are all sharply on the rise um and all
of them at least from my understanding
looking at the research really have
estrogenic components. Estrogen is, you
know, and this isn't to bash estrogen
and estradiol especially, it's a
fantastic hormone. Uh, if it's in
balance and in a good relationship, but
once estrogen gets a little bit too
dominant, so to speak, we start seeing
estrogenics very excitatory in the
nervous system, uh, so much so that it
can push these poor women into a
psychosis of sorts, which is like like a
premenstrual dysphoric disorder. um is
very frightening and they can feel
suicidal, sometimes homicidal even uh
just for this short window of time when
they just have so much estrogen going.
Um and then you know on the other side
of things, estrogen is extremely good at
growing things. Um that's it's a
primordial substance to help things
grow. Um and and so if you think of
endometriosis and polycystic ovaries, uh
a lot of those are just again so much
estrogen, such little progesterone.
Progesterone being the stop gap, you
know, the yin to the yang. progesterone
is saying that's enough, that's plenty,
relax, calm down. Um and and so again,
when I see women in my clinic, it's
primarily for those problems. Uh and
obviously, you know, we get into
fertility and cycles and all those sorts
of things. Um it's it's so rampant right
now. I mean, my young girls here in the
United States, I think nine or 10 is the
average age for menration right now. Um
which is incredibly young. Incredibly
young. Yeah. Same here. Um so the first
thing you get young women on if they are
symptomatical maybe bad night sleeping
sweaty at night is progesterone.
Absolutely. Uh you know I always tell
women progesterone is what uh is to
women what testosterone is to men in a
lot of ways. I think I I think
progesterone is truly the the female
hormone. Um and especially for those
younger women who are miserable. Um, you
know, so many so many men, I think, are
in a good position in terms of
understanding that testosterone is so
vital. Um, I think women are still in a
position where they're seeing hormone
replacement therapy as something they do
when they're older, when when they go
through pmenopause and menopause where
it's it's actually no, it's the same
it's we're in the same boat. Uh, and and
so progesterone and and thyroid by far
probably the most common. Um, but
testosterone as well. Uh, I do treat a
lot of women uh young women with
testosterone. You just have to be
careful if they're, you know, wanting to
get pregnant because it can be, uh, you
know, harmful to the fetus potentially.